We could talk about motivation.
>> Just the the fact that like motivation
changes >> kind of starting you approach the damma
>> kind of starting you approach the damma
with like this uh fanatical attitude
>> the same way you would get really into
any other worldly activity.
And um
then you you you take on the precepts,
you start training in it and
you actually start trying to undo the
tendency that is behind that motivation
for things.
So then you find yourself like
still focusing on um your virtue and
your conduct but then
that uh
that attitude of or like where it's like
you know but I'm I actually thinking
about it
>> like it's not a you know I'm not
passionate about it like I should be
>> then also I should give up passion. So
it
>> you mean like you feeling that um you
don't have enough motivation compared to
when you started out like or or that it
might feel that way?
>> Yeah.
>> Like compared to what you were used to
as as motivation. Uh well yeah like
because >> also like the idea that you might need
>> also like the idea that you might need
to replace it
>> but you only the motivation that you you
know is not actually very helpful.
>> Mhm.
So you mean that you realize
>> you need a new type of motivation fire?
Yeah. >> Yeah. But the thing is that it's not um
>> Yeah. But the thing is that it's not um
it's not it's not up to you to like um
to replace it with something else. It's
when precisely if you take on the
virtue, keep the precepts and then the
motivation that
existed on account of your sensual
activities which is really that like you
like what you said that kind of
passionate almost obsessive um impulse
that's going to have to fade because
that dependent on the type of activities
that are against the precepts.
So, um that's why in a way it's it's
fine if um starting out a person feels
like like they're obsessed with the
dharma and they're they're like kind of
really um cuz you would read that suta
where it says monks you shouldn't cling
to the dharma. You should let it go like
a like a raft like you get to the other
shore. But the thing is people start
saying that when they have a demon like
they just caught in the boat like the
first second and then immediately like
okay so I should let go of the boat now
and you're still not even one centimeter
away from the from the near shore. So
you have to it's not up to you. It's a
it's like you would you it's when you
directly recognize
that the motivation the energy that you
have towards practice
that presents itself as motivation
towards the dharma is actually now like
you see for yourself not that somebody
else told you or something you see for
yourself this is now
taking me away from the actual
um sensation of craving but from that
beginning point of you being passionate
about dharma and really kind of um
firing yourself up to keep the precepts
and and not giving to sensuality and
abandon wholesome things that is closer
to the sessation of craving
than if you
like that's you have less craving when
you do that than than if you were to say
like oh well there's nothing to attain
so we just uh don't don't uh don't
attach to anything even to the dharma as
as a complet beginner who doesn't even
have a review. That would that might
feel from somebody's initial ideas about
what peace is. That might feel better,
but uh that's precisely because it's the
path of least resistance and you're
still fundamentally maintaining the same
um
tendencies like you said, the same
you're still going with the grain.
>> Yes. The wrong kind of indifference.
>> Yeah. like equinimity of of just
>> it's going to be circumstantial as well
like it's going to be if a person feels
that without keeping the precepts
without having gone through that process
of
um restraint. No. Well, but but that
process of feeling like almost um
in a way you could say obsessed with
with restraint and and abandoning the
wrong things that they used to do
without going through that process. If a
person feels that they're aimless and
that they're kind of um able to be at
peace and not be affected by things,
that's only because they still have a
suitable conditions around them that
don't disturb them too much. The only
way that you would be actually
equinimous and unmoved by things, not
based on circumstances, not based on
comforts, not based on what the Buddha
called the the pleasure of the household
life, which are not limited to lay
people like as as a monk, if you if you
still have that dependence on external
comforts, that those are the pleasures
of lay life as they call them. So um
yeah, it's it's only through going
through that training that initially
might feel um unpleasant or or it might
even feel the mind might even try to
convince you that it's wrong because you
know you should be you shouldn't be like
so caring so much about something.
Um, but it's like, okay, well, you have
cancer. You can choose to
You can choose to
not really care and and live and enjoy
each day as it passes and not really
worry about what's going to happen, fact
that you have a terminal illness that
that might kill you at any moment. Or
you can
really see the fact of having cancer as
a problem and uh for the time being,
let's say,
be in a state of more agitation, but
actually be doing something that might
save your life instead of just
letting go in that kind of very early
premature way.
So giving up craving based on craving
appears in somewhere
>> that's valid but in the beginning
>> and then and then then based on that you
at some point you realize wait it's
actually because of this same craving
that I now recognize as the original
suffering then it doesn't apply anymore.
>> Yeah. But then but then that's that has
to happen on its own like not that that
you start like um second guessing
yourself like oh maybe my effort is is
no it's if if if that's if that's what
you feel effort is if that's what is
that what it's um
the direction of effort that you know
well that's the least wrong thing for
you to do at that time and then only
when it becomes apparent why
it's inaccurate then you'll be able to
upgrade it. Otherwise, you're just
acting out of a sense of duty or a sense
of
>> external
um reasoning or or whatever you might
have heard is the right level of effort.
But for you factually,
whatever craving you experience,
whatever defilements you experience,
whatever for you stands for not giving
into that
>> is the practice.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So it is by understanding
what craving is
that all of that under goes a change.
But you cannot now say oh it's time for
me now to start abandoning that craving
which I originally had because you will
be making that choice based on some
great which you then don't see.
>> Yeah. And and
you would also be going back to things
that you should have given up
>> because that's usually what it means to
to say like, "Oh, I'm going to relax."
When when when you're too loose, you've
not you've not actually reached the
right level of tightness and you start
loosening. >> What what it usually means is yet you go
>> What what it usually means is yet you go
back to things that are actually
obstructions. So it's it's more like
everybody starts out too loose. Like
it's it's it's it's there's no way
around it. Um you have to tighten it up.
You have to take on that again even if
it feels painful that determination to
not act out. Give it give up on
wholesome states. uh purify your mind
and inevitably that will result in
going let's say
farther than where the middle way is.
But then when you reach that point and
you feel like you actually see like oh
wait why am I winding myself up
unnecessarily like past this point
there's already nothing in wholesome so
why am I constantly kind of um trying to
push things away farther than that it's
not necessary so then you realize okay
so this is where I need to stay
instead of here you move back here which
means you're still keeping the precepts,
you're still uh restraining your senses,
you're still restraining your speech,
but um you're not finding problems with
everything and nothing. You're not
saying like um
>> it's based on something internal.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It it's now that's going to be
based on something internal because you
have that direct recognition of these
mental states that were driving you to
go too far and you see, oh, that was the
problem. It's not the like the external
It's not the like the external
>> doing.
>> Yeah. It's not it's not even the
external level of renunciation because
in some um sutas the Buddha would talk
about how um and monks in general like
doing aesthetic practices and he would
say like for some people
that would that would be their way of
practicing the middle way. In other
words, it would not be excessive
aestheticism because it's not based on the external
because it's not based on the external
activities that you're doing. It's
whether internally you are just pushing
with it with that sense of duty towards
these external ideals of renunciation or
whether you actually see the mind. You
actually see its inclinations and you're
simply refraining from giving into that.
You don't think in terms of oh I should
do this every day or I should never do
that every day apart from the precepts.
you just think in terms of is there
greed, is there aversion, is there
delusion, do I act out of it or not? And
then yes, for some that might uh result
in in doing a set of practices, but if
you start doing these things
um
and you think that that's all that the
practice is, just keep going as far as
far as you can in that direction. Limit
more, restrict more, um abandon more on
that external level.
You're not even allowing that room to
become aware that oh wait this is this
is this is going too far now.
So you're responding
like a
the mind kind of shows its thoughts that
you notice its desire its desires and
then you are refraining from those
desires rather than
rather than restraining something
first to then get a reaction from the
mind like prot
actually demanding.
>> Yeah. The thing is the the the like if
you're already looking for where the
mind is, that's already a step forward.
Like usually that's not what happens.
What happens is that you have these
abstract notions that certain things are
always rooted in craving and then based
on that you start giving things up and
then I mean that's inevit inevitably how
you start out because the precepts are
just these specific things that you
don't do and you don't see for yourself
where the craving behind those
activities would be but at least if you
were instructed rightly you would be
making the effort to see oh actually
this is about the mind it's not about my
mind specifically. So like not even that
for everyone the same things will be unh
wholesome again apart from the precepts
uh for some for you doing at that
specific time doing one thing could mean
acting out of greed acting out of
aversion for somebody else it isn't uh
but then acting out of these external
notions of what's right and what's wrong
you might even think oh look at him he's
being indulgent right now because you
you you see it all on that level like um
like I I always say like almost like a
list of things that that that you think
are inappropriate and things that are
appropriate. And
if you start looking at your mind, you
realize and and recognizing your mind,
you realize that's actually quite a
burden to have to adhere to these
almost like
external guidelines.
It's it's it's completely divorced
from the basis of where the hindrances
actually are. So which means you're
acting out of them. If you're not seeing
them, >> you're acting out of them automatically.
>> you're acting out of them automatically.
>> Yeah. So conformity to something
external is not what the actual virtue
is. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Even though for most people it may start
like that.
>> Yeah.
>> If if it's the right thing, i.e.
those seven precepts that we were
talking about recently that still starts
out as external. But to conform to that
cannot be equated with being virtuous.
The virtue begins when keeping those
precepts shows you where your mind is
pushing you and then you don't give in.
>> That's the whole point.
>> Yeah. So it's it's like um it's kind of
like a like a
by if you make the right effort on the
basis of even taking on the precepts
semi- blindly let's say just okay I just
don't do these things
>> but you actually make the effort to to
um
see why those things are wrong.
>> Yeah. Then you would see the same thread
underlies a whole bunch of other things
>> that some people might think are fine,
>> some monks might think are fine because
because >> you know it's not explicitly stated in
>> you know it's not explicitly stated in
the vine or something
>> which is still taking that external
thing as a criteria.
>> Yeah. And and it's really your own
notions like like kind of um almost like
making inferences
>> and that's that's completely like that
that's why it's from that point of view
it would always be subjective.
>> Mhm. And then people will be arguing
about like what what standards of
conduct are
>> because they don't see fundamentally
it's it's that um whether you're acting
out of greed aversion or not and that's
not going to manifest in the same way
for everyone.
>> Yeah.
So if someone comes here and they ask
you what is right effort
talks about right effort then what would
you say
it's maintainance of the
[Music] Non acting out
Non acting out
based on seeing the mind when there is
pull towards
particular sense object
and how are you making sure that you're
that it is the actual minds that you are
seeing. So when somebody comes here they've been
So when somebody comes here they've been
reading some book introduction to
Buddhism write no wasteful path right
efforts and prepare to make efforts. So
can you p not right efforts? So you give
that answer it's not wrong but can we
assume that people immediately know what
the mind is and what we mean by pressure
for example
>> and if not
then what would be the right answer
to the question what's the right effort
because does it because Yeah. Uh
realistically what would usually happen
is when the person starts to try to make
effort every thought is a pressure.
>> It's going to feel like that. It's going
to feel like everything is wrong.
Everything that
>> eating a meal can come out of pressure
because I want to stay alive.
>> So So from the beginning if somebody is
like serious and you started out by
saying it might very well feel like they
can't do anything.
>> Yep. Yeah. So, but that's that's now the
symptom that you should see that well
something's wrong because
>> um if if you follow that thread the
final outcome is you have to stop
breathing. >> So because everything you would do would
>> So because everything you would do would
be like oh why am I breathing? Do I have
you you might ask a certain question
like why am I breathing? Do I have
something um to live for
>> to live for and you realize no okay so
that that mean that that means I'm
actually not a craving
but um that's obviously not how it works
because the Buddha was not a Jane so
what what is the mind then what does it
mean to be for the mind to be affected
by pressure and for you to be acting out
of it
which is indeed
what the terms
right efforts from wrong efforts. So you
said it's not wrong, but it's just that
if that's the only thing we say, it's it
will practically still probably not be
right. >> Yeah. Cuz mind can mean anything for for
>> Yeah. Cuz mind can mean anything for for
people. Exactly. Yeah.
>> So I would first not focus on symptoms
on particular
in from my point of view pressures
particulars objects.
objects.
but only see rather this attitude of
being labeled to pressure.
labeled to pressure.
Mhm. Therefore those symptoms those
particulars wouldn't be there if there
this liability
behind this particular symptoms would
not be there.
>> So what are the particular symptoms? For example, For example,
mind
under slotted hindrance. But is that a symptom
slotted hindrance. But is that a symptom
or is that the it it's like background
from particular
manifestations of it?
>> But what is let's say what is this love
interpreter? Is it just the fact that
you don't have energy?
It's like direction
particular direction towards
getting sleepy
>> towards basically lack of energy
>> and it's it's of course manifesting
somehow bodily
>> mentally
>> and those are the symptoms of this
liability >> and mind is on the level of this being
>> and mind is on the level of this being
labeled to those symptoms.
>> So you said you don't focus on the
symptoms.
>> Symptoms are there because of course
there's a bigger problem
>> behind them.
>> Yeah.
>> Otherwise they wouldn't be there.
>> Yeah. So then if you have a mind that's
sleepy or tired,
uh do you try to get rid of the sleep or
tiredness or what do you do?
And you're on the right level. So
not acting out,
>> not getting into it.
>> Factually, when there is pressure to go
to sleep, I would go to sleep at that
very moment.
>> Uhhuh. So,
but so you said and you're on the right
level, how would that manifest?
By not acting out basically. Yeah. But I
mean, of course, you don't um go to
sleep. That's the obvious part. But uh
if you're not doing that, you could
still be fundamentally trying to get rid
of the sleepiness.
Like you would still have that kind of
um underlying
wish that this will go away,
which means you still kind of put the
emphasis on the symptom.
So how would you make sure that truly
truly you see okay this is just a
symptom and I'm not going to be
concerned with this
it might be like
let's say that you say no to go to the
sleep but my can and you can easily end
up directing towards something else with
the same attitude
>> and when at the same time I'm And notice
that this attitude is like the root
problem, >> not the direction towards particulars,
>> not the direction towards particulars,
sleepiness, basically any other
activity. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> That I already can maintain not acting
out. >> But wait, so is that you're saying that
>> But wait, so is that you're saying that
any other bodily activity you would do
would be rooted in the same pressure?
>> No. No. No. Body activity that
it's
So let's say could you just get up and
start walking?
>> No, because let's say that walking would
be rooted on
the same mind kind of. Why?
Because
although I not go to sleep,
>> I find some other
like external
[Music] will do the activity to replace that
will do the activity to replace that
need to go to sleep.
>> What's wrong with that? If that if that
prevents you like if you splash cold
water in your face or you switch on the
light in order to prevent falling asleep
which requires action on your part, if
that prevents you from giving in to the
sleepiness, then why do you say that
that bodily activity is necessary coming
out of the same attitude? For example,
then the sleepiness is can manif
manifested when I sit there and when I
of course going to lay down it's like
lower it's it's going towards that
sleepiness but say when I stay up it's
it's the same attitude for me. Therefore
I rather remain seated. So not changing
any position just
so from that point of view I do not make
any movement
>> but towards or away or replace it
>> but how do you know that that is also
not going under the same attitude like I
should not move
>> because I maintain the knowledge of the
mind is there
>> that that knowledge disappears simply by
standing up
>> or how do you know that the the mental
state that would be behind getting up
and walking is not actually a new
state that is
um
well it's rooted specifically in not
giving into the other the other state.
Yeah. Cuz it sounds like you're saying
that that
if you necessarily if you got up it
would be rooted in the pressure but the
pressure is fundamentally mental. It's
not I don't want to say it would be it
wouldn't be because I didn't do it
basically. And
>> at the moment when I realized that the
this this pressure of going to the sleep
is no longer there.
>> Mhm.
>> It kind of energy manifested
>> because of the knowledge that this mind
is also no longer there. This pressure
this manifestation.
>> Mhm. Basically this entire momentum at
this very moment wasn't there
>> anymore.
>> But but uh does that mean that then you
need to get rid of it in order to have
that energy?
>> What I'm trying to say I need to do
anything rather than just realize that
this state of mind is there and not
going towards this direction. That's all
what I need to do. Yeah. But the the
thing is that the the thing of the
decision to to stay seated and not do
anything that can also be a form of
action like it's not that automatically
because you don't get up like you might
still be doing that out of craving and
then whether the thing goes away or it
stays uh that's secondary because
uh that's secondary because
fundamentally you're still maintaining
yourself alive like that would be the
momentum. The momentum would be that
when pressure arises,
uh, you can't put up with it. You can
only be at peace, quote unquote, when
it's not there.
And so
like enduring things on the right level
would mean even if the pressure is
there, you're not affected by it. So
that even if you're even if the mind is
sleepy, you you you can or the body is
sleepy, whatever, you can distance
yourself from it and see this has arisen
on its own cuz like it's impossible to
have a permanent state of energy. And
even in sutas it would say um the the
basis for sloth and torpour is uh
tiredness, sleepiness, uh sluggishness
after the meal. But the hindrance of
sloth and torpour is the wrong attention
that you would pay to the state of
tiredness, drowsiness and so on. So if
you were to get up but not with
that let's say like you said that
attitude of expecting or hoping that the
pressure of tiredness will go away then
that's the right level that would be the
right level but if you think I I need to
get this to to go away somehow whether
by uh saying staying seated or getting
up fundamentally that is the like the
expectation or the the the
hope to pretty much change something
that wasn't yours to begin with. So like
the peace that you that that you want to
discover and become established in is
the piece of not being bothered by it in
the first place, not the piece of like I
get it to go away and then I'm find
Because fundamentally the mind like the
the chitta
it's not the
it's not that when you have let's say
lustful mind like there will always be
that tendency to confuse lustful mind
with the thoughts that come on account
of the lustful mind
and the natural tendency is to look at
the problem there and then think okay if
I can just get this to go away
by any means necessary
do a concentration technique uh look
somewhere else think about something
else replace it ignore it
>> then
>> then the lustful the lust is gone
>> but the lust
>> is that liability
so that if those um let's say images or
thoughts were to present themselves
you can't be you you can't stay distance
from them. So it's the same with a sloth
and torper like sloth and torper is not
the presence of that pressure of
tiredness is as you said the liability it's the
is as you said the liability it's the
fact that if the body gets tired if
there is sluggishness the mind gets
mixed and involved with it it can't stay
distanced from it. So that's what that's
the right level like it's the it's the
recognition that these things arise on
their own but that the mind the jitta
that you have to tame is that basically
like that um
almost feel it would feel almost like
automatic engagement
engagement
with these pressures that come up
>> and then that's why it's it's it's
called like the opening amidst
confinement when the would talk about
the uh the right view and even somati
because it's not the it's not that you
get rid of the confinement like you you
get rid of these um let's say unpleasant
things that are that might be assailing
you get it rid of your craving in regard
to them and that's the vulnerable truths
like suffering is not the sleepiness
it's not the the lust like the the sign
of beauty it's not the annoyance of of
like the significance of other other
people or other situations being
annoying. It's the craving that then far down the
It's the craving that then far down the
line leads you to act out of lust, act
out of anger, act out of go to sleep,
out of laziness. But that's that's now
like it's not that then if I just
if if I just get rid of those things,
it's it's only really like I'm I'm
undoing the
it's like a like
instead of let's say some object that
you have on the ground, instead of
hammering it fixed onto the ground like
nailing it down so that it doesn't move
no matter what comes, you just stop
things from coming
and that's only ever going to be temp
like that cannot be a reliable
uh freedom and that's why it would keep
coming back like it would feel like
every time these things come back up I
need to deal with them again and again
and again
whereas what you really want to see is
how do I make myself not be liable so
that whether this come comes up or not
it does it's completely irrelevant
What I meant is rather the mere fact of
this choice of not acting out.
>> Mhm.
>> Okay. Without intention to kind of
change the state and they get rid of it
or whatever.
Just recognizing that at this particular
time, at this particular occasion,
there's not acting out
>> the choice of not giving. That's it.
>> But does it need to go away?
>> There wasn't that intention at all.
>> But but but is there still like a sort
of
view or emphasis that if it doesn't go
away, I haven't succeeded?
Would you be able to see that if it
stays there for 10 years, there's no
problem or would you feel like something's still
or would you feel like something's still
missing?
I can tell it was just the recognition
that the the victory the small victory
of not acting out of this might at this
very moment.
>> Yeah, but that's the thing. So like you
can say that it's not acting out but the
the not acting out of the right level
fundamentally depends on whether you see
like it doesn't matter whether this
stays or leaves because my
responsibility is the craving not the
feeling. So even if it remains kind of
assailing you for whatever amount of
time, you need to reach that certainty
that I'm safe here regardless of what
comes up. Because then I see if you then
if there's that that at least that's
what you said. It sounded to me like you
were saying, "Oh, the victory came when
the thing went away."
>> No, no, no. This is not life.
>> Uhhuh.
>> So when what is victory then? the
recognition of that state and not going
to sleep
as a remote basically old habit of
basing. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> Think you surely then what if there
comes a point where you you can't go you
could go to sleep?
>> You wouldn't necessarily be acting out
of
>> Yeah, you could you could go to sleep
>> because otherwise every every um I don't
have to went to sleep would be acting
out of hindrances. Yeah.
>> So let alone getting up as well.
>> I'm not blaming the sleep sleepiness as
if and basically itself but at this
particular instance it was
rooted in hindrance.
>> Yeah. No, of course. Like there would be
a hindrance involved,
>> but uh but I'm just saying like it's
important to keep the emphasis because
it's it's going to happen. It's it's not
um it's not a matter of if
that that kind of view will set back in
that I am fine only when it goes away.
And it's not it's not something that you
will kind of necessarily tell yourself.
It's like to the extent that you feel
any sense of
um vulnerability to suffering
is because to some extent there's still
that desire or that expectation to
control that which is impermanent.
Like if if if that was clarified enough
that that actually isn't the problem,
then you wouldn't even reach the point
where the suffering comes up and then
you need to um kind of not act out and
and get it to go away.
I can tell it's it's more like the waves
of habits constantly acting out
>> and therefore it's like clouds of
clouds that are obstructing this
knowledge that the mind is there
>> and it's like constant this this habit
It's like waves
>> every time
acting out it it basically it creates
this this motion of lack of
knowledge what mind is there.
>> Mhm. But this particular event it's like
reminder that
not acting out equals freedom from
suffering. >> So
>> So
therefore it's like breaking the chain
of automatic habits of the of the old
habits of acting out. So uh uh
but in what sense are they automatic?
It's it's like basically constant choice
of acting out.
>> Constant choice of acting out.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Choice basically it's
choice. >> But uh like how can the cho are you
>> But uh like how can the cho are you
saying the choice happens by itself?
>> No. No. Basically it's
>> right. So then that that that's what I'm
trying to say.
>> Of acting out it's
>> the wave. You cannot say that the wave
is a habit.
Because the habit would be kind of your
engagement with that thing rather if any
wave that might come in and of itself is
not the issue. Habit of choosing
acting out.
>> Uhhuh.
>> Yeah.
>> So the habit of choosing acting out but
the habit is on you not on something
else that
>> comes by itself. So that's like
the point is it might sound like the
same thing, but if there's that
implication of like I'm being almost
like um compromised or threatened
by these things that come on their own,
then that's not the right level. The
right level means recognizing actually
it doesn't matter what comes, I cannot
be threatened except through my own
choice. So that's that's that's what the but
So that's that's that's what the but
then if if
again like
when there's that implication
it's usually not going to be recognized.
That's something that you have to kind
of um
not assume that just saying okay I just
don't act out. You also have to
investigate because sometimes not acting
out will not be the right level like it
won't be seen on the right level
basically. It will still have that
implication of like okay I don't act out
so that it goes away
and then the victory
um again just repeat it would have
nothing to do with whether the thing
went away or not. The victory would be
just recognizing
the level where you're not affected
no matter what comes up.
And then if you recognize that level,
you would see that it doesn't matter
whether you get up or or stay uh seated
because that's not automatically what it
means to act out.
Like you yourself said, it's an
attitude. So attitude attitude is a is a
mental um decision. It's not like just
simply because I um stood up it meant
that I acted out of cravings. Say same
as uh eating even when you're hungry for
that matter eating when you're hungry
doesn't mean that you are acting out of
craving like you have that reflection of
uh I will eat only for the sake of
nourishing the body not for the sake of
entertainment. So in the same way you
could say okay I'll get up not for the
sake of fighting with the sleepiness.
I'm fine if this stays for the next 20
years but I will not do this because I
want it to go away. And that that little
kind of um implication is something
that's up to you. It's not up to the
action that you do. Of course you break
the precepts the implication will always
be wrong. But
uh putting that aside, you could do
almost an endless amount of things not
with the
underlying motivation or hope
that's affected by craving.
And that's how you would actually be
free. Not that you kind of need to
constrict yourself more and more to do
less and less things because you you
don't act out. No, like you recognize
actually acting out is a mental choice
and then you realize like you have that
huge range
of things that
won't be involving you with the danger.
>> So attitude of acting out stands for
craving. >> Yeah. Yeah. Put it that way. So it's
>> Yeah. Yeah. Put it that way. So it's
like um but it's a it's a it's a mental
emphasis. It's a mental
It's a mental
um direction.
In this case to again use that example
of sleepiness. It's
usually it's going to be that hope like
uh you could even be saying oh um this
has risen on its own. This is
impermanent. This is just a bodily
state. I'm not going to be affected by
it. not going to be affected by it. And
you're saying all that because at the
back of your mind still you are
affected. You're you're affected and
you're taking it for granted and hoping
for it to go away. So it's a it's but
it's a it's a it's it will take driven
because one thing is to hear that
information and and like it makes sense.
But then
um again you could be saying that like
oh okay I I I'm going to try to practice
on the right level. I won't try to get
rid of it because I heard that that's
what I have to do. Still that's not what
the um that's not immediately the
solution. The solution is when you
actually see that full extent of craving
that full extent of the acting out and
you see oh wait actually this doesn't
happen by accident.
This isn't just like, oh, it came by
itself and it and it took over. It's
like me overlooking
that uh you could say, yeah, attitude um
inclination tendency just not not seeing
it, taking it for granted.
That's the habit. It's not like the
habit is the specific like going to
sleep or doing this or doing that. The
habit is when pressure manifests,
you don't even see where the line is and
you either uh indulge in it or you try
to get rid of it because you think that
that's what the problem is. So that's a
fundamental habit of ignorance. Not like
that the other things might just
completely be neutral like habits of of
specific things that you might be used
to doing. But when when when
like the habit of craving is on that
much more subtle level of how you relate
to pressure as such as a general
phenomenon regardless of regardless of
its particulars.
And that's why you can have sometimes
even like u there might not be anything
going on like you might have a neutral
feeling let's say uh you're not
particularly pulled by sensuality
aversion um sleepiness anxiety or doubt
but there's that kind of inactivity kind
of lack of anything going on and that is
a pressure in itself.
So because somebody might be expecting
like oh it's only these very kind of
blatant in my face super unh wholesome
things and then if that's not there then
it's like okay well now what nothing's
happening but no that same pressure of
of um sensuality whatever it's the same
kind of um principle that's there of
that uh when the neutral feeling is
there. It's just a
It's just a
you could say a feeling that you either
overlook, take for granted, take it yours, um act
take for granted, take it yours, um act
out of
in whichever direction or you don't. And
that's why it's that's why it says that
if then if you know the neutral feeling,
it's it's going to be pleasant. If you
don't know it, it's going to be
unpleasant. Yeah, I would say that this
is already somewhat of an accomplishment
to factually even make it as a mental.
>> Well, of course. Yeah, you would have to
already have um not acted out of of
pretty much most of the hindrances like
>> Yeah. because somebody can say, oh,
there's these three kinds of feeling and
then they might designate all sorts of
things in a day that I person feeling,
but that's overwhelmingly possibly
wrong. >> So, um so that would hing well not only
>> So, um so that would hing well not only
on the on the on the virtual restraint
now, but also
in order to start recognizing these
things. >> Yeah. And that's the other thing I mean
>> Yeah. And that's the other thing I mean
right so back when we were asking about
the right efforts and you were talking
about seeing the mind like are you going
to see that
like outside of seclusion if if if you
are right always surrounded by people
then is that will it ever be clear
but you designated as mind earlier
because then if somebody asks what is
the right effort. We can say all of
this, but do we not make it clear that
they should put themselves in a
situation of bodily seclusion?
>> Well,
>> or or yeah, or at at least have a fair
amount of hours where you are just
physically on your own. That's going to
be a necessary condition in order to
even see that might. If you don't see
that, then everything that we just
discussed will remain abstract.
>> Yeah. But even just more
I don't think most people are at the
stage where what they need is actually
seclusion. You go seclusion not without
the foundation of the precepts well
established and it's not really going to
lead to the right thing because um
you're acting out now is on a much more
course level.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I was going to come to that
but but I was actually walking backwards
from what he is saying to the seclusion
and then the next step was actually
going to be in in order for you to hold
that seclusion where this neutral
feeling like border more sometimes of
loneliness or right all of that
>> um that's going to come up and in order
to now not be overwhelmed by that it's
going to be possible only if you already
know how to deal with the more course
acting out which is on the level of the
basic precept now
>> there's just no way that that you can
begin to see like what does it mean for
the mind to resist the neutral feeling?
If if the full-on sensual pleasure and
happiness, you immediately jump at it.
>> Uh aversion aversion like or unpleasant
feeling >> uh when manifests when people say things
>> uh when manifests when people say things
that you don't like, things that are
unpleasant for you, you immediately
react. try to kind of um get them to to
not say that or or tell them off or
whatever. There's just no hope. Like you
you're completely out there and this
stuff is like under the radar. You're
not going to see it.
>> Yeah. And you can also make a connection
here like um you know because that
because it's in a sense easier to
recognize that acting out of anger and
ill will and hate speech whether it's
online or elsewhere, right? that that
all of that is unh wholesome. So if you
say to someone that it would be good if
people including myself do less of that
then most people will agree. But what is
often not seen is that if at the same
time you still act out on the desire for
sensuality >> then that is just going to be a whole
>> then that is just going to be a whole
statement. But why is that so? Because
when there's a sensual impulse going up
or right and the and you don't recognize
that and you act out, there's basically
no space between you and that mind.
>> And if that space is not there, there's
just a life of habitual sensual
gratification, instant gratification.
Then when there's an unpleasant feeling,
there's also going to be no space. And
so there will be an immediate acting out
trying to get rid of the thing that you
think is making you feel unpleasant. And
so the connection is that it is that
same mind. So if somebody wants to bring
about a situation where there is not
going to be any acting out of ill will
suppose they have that intention then
that's good and you should restrain
acting out of that aversion and that
annoyance and and that hatred and so on.
But you're going to be very quickly
running into a wall if you do not
simultaneously start also restraining
sensual pleasures. And that is what not
so many people are prepared to do. So
that means that this is a hollow
statement to to then only deal with the
aversion and the ill will in isolation
from potentiality.
>> Yeah. It's it's not necessarily that you
will be acting out of aversion just
because you give
>> but you will fall into then the
superficial management and psychotherapy
techniques. So then you will not be uh
you may not be angry with other people
you know you will not be expressing your
anger but that internal kind of spark of
the the thing coming up in the first
place this this this um discontent or
this this annoyance coming up in the
first place that's not going to change
because >> it's that's yeah like you said it's
>> it's that's yeah like you said it's
maintained by the sensuality like you
are bothered by things not going your
Okay. Because you want things to go your
way >> because you you're used to chasing your
>> because you you're used to chasing your
way.
>> And that's precisely what desire and
sensuality is.
>> Yeah.
>> So if you didn't have that, as we've
said before,
>> you didn't have your way that you're
chasing, then why would you be bothered when
then why would you be bothered when
things don't blow your way?
>> Yeah.